I live in South Central.
أنا أعيش في منطقة ساوث سنترال
This is South Central:
هذه هي منطقة ساوث سنترال
liquor stores,
متاجر خمور،
fast food,
وجبات سريعة،
vacant lots.
مناطق شاغرة.
So the city planners, they get together and they figure
وفي مجلس المدينة يجتمع المخططون ويتوصلون إلى أنهم
they're going to change the name South Central to make it represent something else,
سيغيرون الاسم ساوث سنترال ليجعلونه يمثل شيئاً آخر
so they change it to South Los Angeles,
لذا غيروه إلى (جنوب لوس أنجلوس)،
like this is going to fix what's really going wrong in the city.
وكأن هذا سيحل مشاكل المدينة الحقيقية.
This is South Los Angeles. (Laughter)
هذا جنوب لوس أنجلوس. (ضحك).
Liquor stores,
متاجر خمور،
fast food,
وجبات سريعة،
vacant lots.
مناطق شاغرة.
Just like 26.5 million other Americans,
تماماً كـ 26,5 ملايين أمريكيين آخرين،
I live in a food desert,
أنا أعيش في صحراء من الأطعمة،
South Central Los Angeles,
منطقة ساوث سنترال في لوس أنجلوس.
home of the drive-thru and the drive-by.
مستقر مطاعم الـ drive-thru والـ drive-by.(= مطاعم وأنت تعبر, وأنت تمر)
Funny thing is, the drive-thrus are killing more people than the drive-bys.
والمضحك أن مطاعم الـ drive-thru تقتل أكثر من مطاعم الـ drive-by.
People are dying from curable diseases
الناس يموتون بسبب أمراض يمكن معالجتها.
in South Central Los Angeles.
في منطقة ساوث سنترال، لوس أنجلوس.
For instance, the obesity rate in my neighborhood
على سبيل المثال، نسبة السمنة في حيي
is five times higher than, say, Beverly Hills,
تبلغ خمسة أضعاف النسبة في بيفيرلي هلز،
which is probably eight, 10 miles away.
والتي تبعد حوالي ١٢ أو ١٦ كيلومتراً.
I got tired of seeing this happening.
لقد سئمت من مشاهدة هذا يحدث.
And I was wondering, how would you feel
وكنت أتسائل، كيف ستشعر،
if you had no access to healthy food,
إن لم تستطع الحصول على غذاء صحي،
if every time you walk out your door you see the ill effects
إن كنت كلما خرجت من المنزل ترى الأمراض
that the present food system has on your neighborhood?
التي يسببها نظام الغذاء الحالي لحيك؟
I see wheelchairs bought and sold
أنا أرى كراسي متحركة تشترى وتباع
like used cars.
كالسيارات المستخدمة.
I see dialysis centers popping up like Starbucks.
وأرى مراكز غسيل كلى تظهر كأنها مقاهي (Starbucks.).
And I figured, this has to stop.
وقد قررت أن قد طفح الكيل.
So I figured that the problem is the solution.
وتوصلت إلى أن المشكلة هي الحل.
Food is the problem and food is the solution.
الطعام هو المشكلة والطعام هو الحل.
Plus I got tired of driving 45 minutes round trip
بالإضافة إلى أني سئمت من القيادة لـ ٤٥ دقيقة
to get an apple that wasn't impregnated with pesticides.
فقط لأحصل على تفاحة لم تًملأ بالمبيدات.
So what I did, I planted a food forest in front of my house.
فكان ما فعلته، أني أنشأت مزرعة غذاء أمام داري.
It was on a strip of land that we call a parkway.
كانت على قطاع من الأرض نسميه متنزه،
It's 150 feet by 10 feet.
مساحته ٤٥ متراً في ٣ أمتار.
Thing is, it's owned by the city.
لكن المشكلة أنها ملك المدينة.
But you have to maintain it.
ولكن تلزمك صيانتها.
So I'm like, "Cool. I can do whatever the hell I want,
فكانت ردة فعلي: "حسناً. يمكنني فعل ما يحلو لي،
since it's my responsibility and I gotta maintain it."
بما أني مسؤول عنها وعلي صيانتها."
And this is how I decided to maintain it.
وهذه طريقتي لصيانتها.
So me and my group, L.A. Green Grounds, we got together
فقد اجتمعت أنا ومجموعتي (L.A. Green Grounds)
and we started planting my food forest, fruit trees,
وبدأنا بزراعة غابة الأطعمة، أشجار فاكهة،
you know, the whole nine, vegetables.
خضروات، وهلم جراً.
What we do, we're a pay-it-forward kind of group,
ما نفعله، هو أننا مجموعة تمول نفسها،
where it's composed of gardeners from all walks of life,
وهي متكونة من بستانين من شتى مجالات الحياة،
from all over the city, and it's completely volunteer,
ومن جميع أرجاء المدينة، و خيرية تماماً،
and everything we do is free.
وكل ما نقدمه بلا مقابل.
And the garden, it was beautiful.
والحديقة كانت جميلة.
And then somebody complained.
ثم قدم أحدهم شكوى.
The city came down on me,
فتواصلت المدينة معي،
and basically gave me a citation saying that I had to remove my garden,
وأعطوني إشعاراً بلزوم إزالة حديقتي،
which this citation was turning into a warrant.
ثم تصاعد هذا الإشعار إلى قضية.
And I'm like, "Come on, really?
فكان جوابي: أجادّون أنتم؟
A warrant for planting food on a piece of land
قضية بتهمة زراعة طعام في قطعة أرض
that you could care less about?" (Laughter)
لا تسمن ولا تغني من جوع ؟ (ضحك)
And I was like, "Cool. Bring it."
ثم أجبتهم: حسناً، أروني ما لديكم.
Because this time it wasn't coming up.
لأنكم لن تنتصروا هذه المرة.
So L.A. Times got ahold of it. Steve Lopez did a story on it
وصحيفة ( L.A. Times ) علمت بالأمر، وكتب Steve Lopez عن القصة،
and talked to the councilman,
وتحدث مع المحافظ،
and one of the Green Grounds members,
وأحد أعضاء المجموعة،
they put up a petition on Change.org,
وأنشأوا التماساً على Change.org،
and with 900 signatures, we were a success.
وقد نجحنا بجمعنا ٩٠٠ توقيع.
We had a victory on our hands.
وكان النصر لنا.
My councilman even called in and said how they endorse
حتى أن المحافظ هاتفني وأخبرني بمدى تأييدهم
and love what we're doing.
وحبهم لأفعالنا.
I mean, come on, why wouldn't they?
وكيف لا بربكم؟
L.A. leads the United States in vacant lots that the city actually owns.
لوس أنجلوس تملك أكبر مساحة من المناطق الشاغرة في الولايات المتحدة.
They own 26 square miles of vacant lots.
فهي تملك ما يبلغ 68 كيلومتراً مربعاً من الناطق الشاغرة.
That's 20 Central Parks.
هذا ما يعادل ٢٠ متنزهاً في حجم الـ ( Central Park ).
That's enough space to plant 725 million tomato plants.
وهي مساحة تكفي لزراعة ٧٢٥ مليون نبتة طماطم.
Why in the hell would they not okay this?
فكيف يمكن أن لا يعجبهم هذا؟
Growing one plant will give you 1,000, 10,000 seeds.
فزراعة نبتة واحدة سينتج لنا بين ألفٍ وعشرة آلاف بذرة.
When one dollar's worth of green beans
بينما فاصوليا خضراء بقيمة دولار واحد
will give you 75 dollars' worth of produce.
ستنتج لنا محصولاً بقيمة ٧٥ دولاراً.
It's my gospel, when I'm telling people, grow your own food.
إنه مذهبي في الحياة، أن أخبر الناس بأن يزرعوا طعامهم بأنفسهم.
Growing your own food is like printing your own money.
بزرع طعامك بنفسك كأنه طباعة مالك بنفسك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
See, I have a legacy in South Central.
وإني لدي تراث في منطقة South Central.
I grew up there. I raised my sons there.
فقد نشأت هناك. وربيت بنيَّ هناك.
And I refuse to be a part of this manufactured reality
وأنا أرفض أن أكون مشاركاً في هذا الواقع الجاهز،
that was manufactured for me by some other people,
الذي صنعه أناس آخرون.
and I'm manufacturing my own reality.
وأنا أصنع الواقع الخاص بي.
See, I'm an artist.
فأنا كفنان.
Gardening is my graffiti. I grow my art.
والزراعة بالنسبة لي كأنها جرافيتي. وأنا أزرع عملي الفني.
Just like a graffiti artist, where they beautify walls,
تماماً كرسام جرافيتي يجمّل الجدران،
me, I beautify lawns, parkways.
أجمل أنا المروج والمتنزهات.
I use the garden, the soil, like it's a piece of cloth,
أنا أستخدم المزرعة، تربتها، كأنها قطعة قماش،
and the plants and the trees,
والنباتات والأشجار،
that's my embellishment for that cloth.
هي زخارفي لهذا القماش.
You'd be surprised what the soil could do
وإن التربة ستفاجئكم،
if you let it be your canvas.
إن اتخذتموها لوحة فنية.
You just couldn't imagine how amazing a sunflower is
ولا يمكنكم تخيل روعة دوار الشمس
and how it affects people.
وأثره على الناس.
So what happened?
وما كانت النتيجة؟
I have witnessed my garden become a tool for the education,
لقد شهدت حديقتي تتحول إلى أداة تعليم،
a tool for the transformation of my neighborhood.
أداة تحول في حيي.
To change the community, you have to change the composition of the soil.
فلتُغير المجتمع، عليك تغيير تركيب التربة.
We are the soil.
ونحن التربة.
You'd be surprised how kids are affected by this.
وتأثر الأطفال بهذا الأمر قد يفاجئكم حقاً.
Gardening is the most therapeutic
فالزراعة هي أنجع وأجرأ وسيلة علاج
and defiant act you can do,
يمكنك اتخاذها،
especially in the inner city.
خصوصاً في داخل المدينة.
Plus you get strawberries.
علاوة على أنك تحصل على الفراولة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I remember this time,
ومازلت أذكر ذاكم الوقت،
there was this mother and a daughter came,
حينما أتت أم وابنتها،
it was, like, 10:30 at night, and they were in my yard,
قرابةَ السابعةِ مساءً، وكانتا في فناءي،
and I came out and they looked so ashamed.
فخرجت لهما وكانتا مخزيتان.
So I'm like, man, it made me feel bad that they were there,
وشعرت بالحزن لهما،
and I told them, you know, you don't have to do this like this.
وقلت لهما: أتعلمان؟ أنا لا ألزمكم فعل هذا.
This is on the street for a reason.
فلسبب ما كانت حديقتنا في الشارع.
It made me feel ashamed to see people
وشعرت بالعار عند رؤيتي لأناس جوعى
that were this close to me that were hungry,
قريبين مني لهذه الدرجة،
and this only reinforced why I do this,
وهذا مما شد عزمي فيما أفعل،
and people asked me, "Fin, aren't you afraid
وقد سألني الناس: فن، ألا تخشى
people are going to steal your food?"
أن يسرق الناس طعامك؟
And I'm like, "Hell no, I ain't afraid they're gonna steal it.
وكان جوابي: بالطبع لا أخشى أن يُسرق طعامي!
That's why it's on the street.
إنه في الشارع لهذا السبب فقط.
That's the whole idea.
ليس المغزى إلا هذا.
I want them to take it, but at the same time,
أريدهم أن يأخذوه، ولكن في نفس الوقت،
I want them to take back their health."
أريدهم أن يستعيدوا صحتهم أيضاً.
There's another time when I put
ومرة أخرى كنت قد زرعت
a garden in this homeless shelter in downtown Los Angeles.
حديقة في مأوى مشردين في وسط لوس أنجلوس.
These are the guys, they helped me unload the truck.
وهؤلاء هم، الذين ساعدوني في تفريغ الشاحنة.
It was cool, and they just shared the stories
وكان الأمر رائعاً، وقد شاركوا قصصهم،
about how this affected them and how
وكيف أن هذا قد أثر فيهم،
they used to plant with their mother and their grandmother,
وكيف كانوا يزرعون مع أمهاتهم وجداتهم،
and it was just cool to see how this changed them,
وقد سعدت جداً برؤيتي كيف غيرهم هذا الأمر،
if it was only for that one moment.
وإن لم أجنِ منه شيئاً غير هذه اللحظة.
So Green Grounds has gone on to plant
ومجموعة Green Grounds استمرت في زراعة
maybe 20 gardens.
٢٠ حديقة تقريباً.
We've had, like, 50 people come to our dig-ins
وكان يأتي حوالي ٥٠ شخصاً لمناطق الحرث
and participate, and it's all volunteers.
ويشاركوننا، وقد كانوا جميعاً متطوعين.
If kids grow kale, kids eat kale.
إن يزرع الأطفال الكرنب، يأكلوا الكرنب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If they grow tomatoes, they eat tomatoes. (Applause)
إن يزرعوا الطماطم، يأكلوا الطماكم. (تصفيق)
But when none of this is presented to them,
ولكن إن لم يقدم لهم منهما شيء،
if they're not shown how food affects the mind and the body,
إن لم يروا كيف يؤثر الطعام على العقل والجسم،
they blindly eat whatever the hell you put in front of them.
فسيأكلون بتهور كل ما يوضع أمامهم.
I see young people
أنا أرى شباباً
and they want to work,
يريدون العمل،
but they're in this thing where they're caught up --
ولكنهم يقعون في هذه المشكلة ــ
I see kids of color and they're just on this track
وأرى أطفالاً سمراً يسيرون على الطريق
that's designed for them,
الذي قد مُهِّد لهم،
that leads them to nowhere.
والذي لا يقودهم إلى هدف.
So with gardening, I see an opportunity
لذا بالزراعة، أرى فرصة،
where we can train these kids
أنه يمكننا تدريب هؤلاء الأطفال
to take over their communities,
ليعتنوا بمجتمعاتهم،
to have a sustainable life.
وليقفوا على أرجلهم.
And when we do this, who knows?
وإن نجحنا، فمن يدري؟
We might produce the next George Washington Carver.
ربنا يخرج منا جورج واشنطن كارفر الجديد.
but if we don't change the composition of the soil,
لكن إن لم نغير تركيب التربة،
we will never do this.
فلن ننجح أبداً.
Now this is one of my plans. This is what I want to do.
والآن هذه إحدى خططي، هذا ما أريد تحقيقه.
I want to plant a whole block of gardens
أريد أن أزرع حول عمارة سكنية بأكملها،
where people can share in the food in the same block.
ليتشارك سكانها في طعامهم.
I want to take shipping containers
أريد أن آخذ حاويات الشحن،
and turn them into healthy cafes.
وأحولها إلى مقاهي صحية.
Now don't get me wrong.
ولكن لا تسيئوا فهمي.
I'm not talking about no free shit,
أنا لا أتحدث عن خدمات مجانية،
because free is not sustainable.
لأن ما كان بالمجان فلن يستمر.
The funny thing about sustainability,
والمضحك في شأن الاستمرارية:
you have to sustain it.
أن الشيء يجب أن يستمر.
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
What I'm talking about is putting people to work,
فما أتحدث عنه هو توفير فرص عمل للناس،
and getting kids off the street, and letting them know
وإيواء الأطفال من الشوارع، وجعلهم يختبرون
the joy, the pride and the honor in growing your own food,
الفرح، الفخر والشرب في زرع طعامهم بيدهم،
opening farmer's markets.
فاتحين أسواق للمزارعين.
So what I want to do here,
فما أريد فعله هنا،
we gotta make this sexy.
هو جعل هذا جذاباً.
So I want us all to become ecolutionary renegades,
أريد أن نكون جميعنا الثوار من أجل البيئة،
gangstas, gangsta gardeners.
عصابات المزارعين.
We gotta flip the script on what a gangsta is.
لا بد أن نعكس مفهوم ما العصابة.
If you ain't a gardener, you ain't gangsta.
إن لم تكن من المزارعين، فلست من العصابة.
Get gangsta with your shovel, okay?
بمجرفتك تنتمي للعصابة، واضح؟
And let that be your weapon of choice.
ولتكن هي سلاحك المفضل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So basically, if you want to meet with me,
وإن أردتم رؤيتي،
you know, if you want to meet,
إن أردتم مقابلتي،
don't call me if you want to sit around in cushy chairs
لا تهاتفوني إن كنتم تريدون الجلوس على الكراسي الوثيرة،
and have meetings where you talk about doing some shit --
وعقد اجتماعات تتحدثون فيها عن فعل شيء ما ــ
where you talk about doing some shit.
"تتحدثون" عن فعل شيء ما.
If you want to meet with me, come to the garden
إن أردتم أن تجتمعوا بي، تعالوا إلى المزرعة،
with your shovel so we can plant some shit.
بمجرفتكم لـ "نزرع" شيئاً ما.
Peace. Thank you.
والسلام. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق).
Thank you. (Applause)
أشكركم. (تصفيق)